FELIPE TAHA SANT'ANA, Ph.D.

+48-882-844-704 | ftahas@proton.me | ftahas.github.io

in ftsantana | 🕥 ftahas | 🎔 ftsantan | 📵 ORCID | 🗲 Scholar

Introduction

I am a scientist with an interdisciplinary background on theoretical physics, electrical engineering, and computer science. During my undergraduate studies, I worked on numerical techniques for astroparticle physics problems. Then, I started working on AI applied to autonomous robots until I finished my M.Sc. diploma on the field, acquiring extensive experience on machine learning techniques. Since then, during my Ph.D. in theoretical physics and in my postdoc positions, I acquired an extensive expertise on interacting quantum systems, integrable models, quantum field theories, mathematical physics, and AMO physics in general. In addition, I have experience in the private sector, where I have worked on financial models and data science. Currently, I am a Polonez Bis fellow at the Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, working on integrable quantum field theories under the project CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality.

EDUCATION

• University of São Paulo

04/2020

Ph.D. in Physics

São Carlos, Brazil

- Keywords: Bose gases, optical lattice, quantum phase transition, 1d interacting systems.
- Thesis: A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the one-dimensional interacting Bose gas. arXiv:2006.13100; teses.usp

• University of São Paulo

07/2015

M.Sc. in Electrical Engineering

São Carlos, Brazil

- Keywords: Autonomous robots, dynamical environments, collision probability estimation.
- · Dissertation: Estimação de probabilidade de colisão com obstáculos móveis para navegação autônoma. teses.usp

University of São Paulo

07/2012

B.Sc. in Physics

São Carlos, Brazil

EXPERIENCE

• Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences [

11/2022 - 10/2024

Assistant Professor

Warsaw, Poland

- NCN Polonez Bis 1 Fellow
- Principal Investigator of the project CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality

• Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw [

10/2020 - 09/2022

Assistant Professor

Warsaw, Poland

- Postdoctoral researcher within the NCN Sonata project "Dynamic correlation functions of quantum integrable models: in and beyond the equilibrium" headed by Miłosz Panfil.
- Institut de Physique de Nice, Universitè Côte D'Azur [�]

06/2018 - 05/2019

Ph.D. Researcher

Financial Analyst

• Doctoral researcher under CAPES/COFECUB bilateral collaboration.

Nice, France

- São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paulo [
- Ph.D. Researcher

04/2016 - 04/2020 São Carlos, Brazil

- Doctoral researcher within project "Bose gases in optical lattices" headed by F.E.A. dos Santos.
- Luz Financial Solutions []

São Carlos, Brazil

2015

• São Carlos School of Engineering [

03/2013-07/2015

M.Sc. Researcher

São Carlos, Brazil

- $\circ \ Master \ student \ within \ the \ project \ "Dynamic \ environments \ in \ autonomous \ robotics" \ headed \ by \ Valdir \ Grassi \ Jr.$
- Warthog Robotics []

2012-2013

AI Developer

São Carlos, Brazil

TEACHING

• Quantum Field Theory

Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences

◦ Lecture notes

2023-2024

Warsaw, Poland

Statistical Physics

 Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw
 Quantum Mechanics
 Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw
 Computational Physics

 Statistical Physics

 Warsaw, Poland

 Computational Physics
 2017

• Computational Physics São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paylo

PROJECTS

• CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality November 2022 - October 2024 Keywords: Quantum Field Theories, Integrable models, 1d interacting systems

 Project No. 2021/43/P/ST2/02904 co-funded by the National Science Centre and the European Union Framework Programme for Research and Innovation Horizon 2020 under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant agreement no. 945339.

PUBLICATIONS

 $C{=}Conference, J{=}Journal, P{=}Preprint, S{=}In\ Submission, T{=}Thesis$

São Carlos, Brazil

10-14 July 2023

December 2020

- [P.1] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Hui Liu, Two-spinon effects on the thermal Tonks-Girardeau gas, arXiv:2410.20929.
- [J.1] Oleksandr Gamayun, Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Kubo-Martin-Schwinger relation for an interacting mobile impurity, Phys. Rev. Research 5, 043265, 2023. arXiv:2308.06482
- [J.2] Oleksandr Gamayun, Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Mobile impurity in a one-dimensional gas at finite temperatures, Phys. Rev. A 106, 023305, 2022. arXiv:2202.07657
- [J.3] Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, The relevant excitations for the one-body function in the Lieb-Liniger model, J. Stat. Mech. (2021) 073103. arXiv:2104.10491
- [T.1] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the one-dimensional interacting Bose gas, University of São Paulo thesis repository arXiv:2006.13100
- [J.4] F. T. Sant'Ana, F. Hébert, V. Rousseau, M. Albert, P. Vignolo, Scaling properties of Tan's contact: Embedding pairs and correlation effect in the Tonks-Girardeau limit, *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 063608 (2019). arXiv:1908.08714
- [J.5] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Axel Pelster, and Francisco Ednilson Alves dos Santos, Finite-temperature degenerate pergutbation theory for bosons in optical lattices, *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 043609 (2019). arXiv:1906.09661
- [J.6] M. Kübler, F. T. Sant'Ana, F. E. A. dos Santos, and A. Pelster, Improving mean-field theory for bosons in optical lattices via degenerate perturbation theory, *Phys. Rev. A* **99**, 063603 (2019).arXiv:1804.08689
- [C.1] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana et al., Warthog Robotics Team Description Paper 2012, Latin American Robotics Competition Symposium (2012).

TALKS AND POSTERS

 Correlation aspects of interacting quantum systems in reduced dimensionality 	December 2022
BEC seminar, CFT PAN, Warsaw, Poland	
The relevant excitations for the one-body function in the Lieb-Liniger model	20/02 - 04/03, 2022
São Paulo School of Advanced Science on Quantum Fluids and Applications, São Carlos, Brazil	
 Understanding the important excitations in the Lieb-Liniger model 	March 2022
Student workshop on integrability, 2022, Hannover, Germany	
Correlation features of interacting bosons	October 2021
Condensed matter physics seminar, FUW, Warsaw, Poland	

• A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the interacting Bose gas
Condensed matter physics seminar, FUW, Warsaw, Poland

• Bosons in optical lattices 30/01 - 10/02, 2017 School on Interaction of Light with Cold Atoms, São Paulo, Brazil

SKILLS

• Programming Languages: Fortran, C, C++, Python, HTML, Julia, R

Correlation aspects of interacting quantum systems in one dimension

International Conference on Statistical Physics - SIGMAPHI 2023, Chania, Greece

- Systems and softwares: Linux, LaTeX, Mathematica, MatLab, JupyterLab, ROS
- Specialized Areas: Data Science, Machine Learning
- Research Skills: Quantum Systems, Quantum Field Theory, AMO Physics, Integrability, AI, Autonomous Robots
- Languages: Portuguese (Native), English (Professional Proficiency), Spanish (Intermediate), Polish (Basic)